{
  "reference_number": "10412",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a 2050 target in legislation now",
      "answer_index": 0,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Long-Lived Gases and Stabilised Short-Lived Gases - Long-lived gases to net zero by 2050 while also stabilising short-lived gases",
      "answer_index": 12,
      "notes": "While option 2 poses more challenges to agriculture than option 1 poses under present practices and conditions, it is likely that in\n the thirty year time frame advances in science and technology will make the option to stabilize emissions of short-lived gases more\n\n realistic than it might appear in the shorter term. The mood of the times both nationally and internationally requires governments to\n be seen to be taking action. However, particularly at the domestic level, this adjustment needs to be seen as necessary and realistic.\n\n Achieving such a goal must be managed in a context of helping the productive sector to adapt, and operate within the defined\n parameters, rather than being seen to do the 'right thing' by international standards and disregarding the challenges these changes\n pose for the productive sector."
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "The proposed 2050 target is to encourage NZ to develop strategies to continue to devleop and maintain a lifestyle and economy that\n respects and protects the environment, both domestically and internationally.. While purchasing overseas carbon units provides am\n option to help acheive the zero emissions target on paper, it would be seem preferable that they be seen as a option to satisfy\n\n internationally imposed specific targets on exports and to stay on target while science and technology work towards solutions to\n challenges such as fuel poverty, at any given time, rather than as an intrinsic part of achieving the target.."
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "Yes - each incoming Government should have the option to review the third budget in the sequence",
      "answer_index": 14,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Do you agree with the considerations we propose that the Government and the Climate Change Commission take into account when advising on and setting budgets? See p44 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 6,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "The Government should be mindful that on-going solutions and adaptations will come from within many industries as they work to\nreduce emissions. If not represented on the Climate Change Commission, it would be important for the Government to have access\n\nto the expertise of those with knowledge of public and private innovations and technology development systems, particularly in the\nprimary production sector."
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": "Advising the Government on policy settings in the NZ ETS",
      "answer_index": 6,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "With the inclusion of tjhe 'Desirable, but non -essential, expertise,' in particular of those with 'knowledge of the public and private\n\ninnovation and techniology development system.'"
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "15. The Government has proposed a number of new functions to help us adapt to climate change. Do you agree with the proposed functions? See p47 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 13,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "Do you have any other comments you'd like to make?",
      "question_index": 16,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "The productive sector is a major contributor to the country's economy, and to the food supply both domestically and internationlally.\n\nEvery aspect of the expertise suggessted for the Cliimate Change Commission is to be found in the productive sector along with\noften generations of understanding and respect for the environment. It is hoped that the sector is recognised as a valuable\n\nreference resource for establishing climate change pollices and emissions targets."
    }
  ]
}
